Alright friends, welcome back and after we talked about object oriented programming,
the four principles that lie beneath that are the foundations of object oriented programming
at any object oriented programming language for that matter, we go on and talk about
two significant concepts which are at the core of everything that you do in an object oriented
programming language not just in Java and obviously we're just going to talk about the
implementation of those two concepts in Java terms but first let's have a look at them
in literary sense and I'll just walk you through again with real world analogies to understand
them and those concepts are objects and classes and once you understand them you would
be in great shape to write a precise, intelligent and smarter code in the Java programming
language.
So let's just have a look at what a class is followed by what an object is, right?
I'll just do it here for you to start with a real world analogy, so classes now they're
like an idea, right?
They're an idea right here in your mind, the nowhere else they're again not something which
is tangible that's something which you can feel physically, right?
They're just a prototype, a blueprint of something else to come later on and that's something
else to come later on is what we call an object, right?
So class is a definition, a prototype, a blueprint, an idea and object is its implementation
and a real world example of that again, you can take any examples that come to your mind,
one of my classic examples in my sessions is the idea of the almighty and that is of the
idea of humans, right?
So now think about it if almighty, mostly first, before bringing humans to planet Earth would
have thought about it and would have some sort of an idea in their mind what a human's
going to be looked like and let's just talk about this analogy and what I'll do is I'll
say for example, this is your idea of human, right?
And now humans have certain properties, they have legs, they have arms, they have eyes,
they have mouth, they have a heart for example, right?
And on the other side, humans also have walk, they have, for example, the property move,
they have seat, they have air and they have breathe and they have cry and they have smile
and other properties that all of us humans have, right?
All of us share the same properties.
Now, think about it, the left hand side properties and the right hand side properties
are interrelated because now walk without legs would make no sense, breathe without a heart
would make no sense, eat without a mouth would make no sense, see without an eye would
make no sense, punch for example, or say you hit someone, hit is a property, hit without
arms, that would make no sense, a smile without a mouth would make no sense.
That's why I'll say they're interdependent on each other and these are the sort of properties
any class would have, think about this human of this idea as a class, right?
And think about these two as properties, right?
And the right hand side properties, we refer to them as core, which operates on data, right?
Core, which operates on data as I said, walk without legs makes no sense, see without
eyes makes no sense here without ears would make no sense.
That's why I said code that operates on data.
So these are the kind of properties that at any moment of time you would have in a class,
right?
Not just in a human class, right?
And in programming terms, we call these properties as now data as variables, right?
And we call code as methods or functions, right?
So this is the kind, this is the kind of stuff at any moment of time, which you would
have in a class, right?
And this class just as an idea by itself, it doesn't have any physical presence, because
almighty, before bringing humans to earth would have written it somewhere, maybe on any note
taking app if they would have access it at that time, a rough piece of paper or a sticky
pad, but this is what it would have looked like before bringing humans to earth, right?
And that physical implementation now, what is what you and me see in the form of a body
is what we call as an object, an object of of type human, right, of class human.
So class, so now for example, then this thing here becomes your object, when a new human
baby is born, we say this is an object of the class human, right?
And you know, when a new object of human is created in the world, that means when a new
born baby comes to the world, right?
And we say, oh, this human baby is able to walk moosey here, breathe, try and smile and
run and has legs, arms, eyes, mouth and heart.
So that means is a human congratulations, right?
That's how we think about it.
So this is something which has physical presence, right?
So this is something tangible.
So what do we call an object of a class, an object, as you would hear, or read it or
see it online, they say an object is an instance of a class, but you cannot just be limited
to this definition, just define it in your own terms, I would say an object is a physical
manifestation of the idea of a class, it's a physical manifestation, it's a personification
of that idea, which you see in real, which you feel in real, right, a human class, it's an
abstract model, right, just an idea, but an object is its implementation as a set of physical
manifestation of personification, right?
And then how do we go about this stuff is, why is this great?
Because there's just one idea, but think about it, how many humans have come until now
in this planet Earth, into this planet Earth, right?
How many have lived, how many have died, and how many keep continuing to come as well,
like billions, died, billions, came in, blooms, billions, more good follow in all probabilities,
and but the idea is just one, that is it just again helps you to just write it once, but
use it as many as times in different forms and shapes, but all of a sheer similar properties,
where I just took in one example of class human.
So think about it, what other analogies could come to your mind.
You can think about ideas like a smartphone that is another idea of a class, but just
revolt around as I say, with the idea of classes and objects all around us, whatever
you see is an object all around you, right?
And that obviously has some basis somewhere, has an idea somewhere that's called a class,
like for example, you and me would have a table, right, that is an object, but has a basis
somewhere that's a class table, we have the lamp, class and object, you have the, you have
the monitor, you have the laptop, you have the water bottle, these are all classes and
objects, right?
Just makes it so much better, just make it so much convenient and easy for you to understand
these concepts when you take real world analogies, so that's the idea of a class, that's
the idea of an object.
And in the next video, I'm going to tell you if all my people have been in Java developer,
how would have they defined this class human and how would have they created an object?
So implementation coming on for you in the next video.